Guide to the Brazil and Portugal Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Brazil and Portugal collection
1639-1907
MS 1781
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
(2 boxes)
A collection of correspondence; writings; and published illustrated materials from and about Brazil related to Imperial Brazil, religious, economic, and geographic concerns. There is one item under the heading Portugal: a letter of condolence upon the death of a distant relative of Vasco de Gama.
Existence and Location of Copies
The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 2013-M-024, is available on microfilm from Gale Group, Farmington Hills, Michigan.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials have been assembled from various collections and acquired from several individuals. They include materials transferred from the Latin American Collection Curator, Yale University Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 2013-M-024, is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 254 instead of the originals.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by country, and by date within the country, and one accession.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of correspondence; writings; and published illustrated materials from and about Brazil, and is arranged by date. The description of each item includes, when possible, its author, title, place of origin, and a summary of its contents. When an item is a copy of an original, it is arranged by the date of the original. The date field, however, contains the date of the copy itself, not the original. The date of the original is included in the summary description of the item.
Amazon River Region; Brazil -- History -- Empire, 1822-1889; Brazil -- Religion; Brazil; Portugal -- History
- Inventory, 1639-1907
  Scope and Contents
  This collection includes a series of letters, mostly thank you notes from the emperor and empress of Brazil to various Brazilian cardinals. Also found is a miscellaneous copy volume of writings about the Amazon River. The only item from Portugal is a letter by a cosmographer concerning the death of a descendant of Vasco de Gama.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Patrons must use FILM HM 254 instead of the originals.
  - Brazil
    - Title: Letter by Vicente [Ribero?] to [Francisco Ribero?]. Description: Letter concerning expenses incurred by/on behalf of Antonio/a de Miranda during a seventeen month period., 1639 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by King João VI to Cardinal Rivarola. Place: Saco da Bemposta. Description: Handwritten letter by the king of Portugal thanking the cardinal for his Christmas present, with typescript English summary., 1826 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by the Empress Thereza Christina Maria to Cardinal Bernetti. Place: Rio de Janeiro. Description: Handwritten letter from the empress of Brazil thanking the cardinal for his Christmas greetings, with typescript English summary., 1844 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by the Empress Thereza Christina Maria to Cardinal Casoni. Place: Rio de Janeiro. Description: Handwritten letter from the empress of Brazil to the cardinal thanking him for his Christmas greetings of last year, with typescript English summary., 1860 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by the Emperor Dom Pedro II to Cardinal Bilio. Place: Rio de Janeiro. Description: Handwritten letter from the emperor of Brazil to the cardinal thanking him for his Christmas greetings, with typescript English summary., 1870 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by Imperial Princess Isabella, Regent, to Cardinal Bilio. Place: Rio de Janeiro. Description: Letter from the regent, in the name of her father, Emperor Dom Pedro II, to the cardinal thanking him for his Christmas greetings, with typescript English summary., 1872 March 2 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by the Empress Thereza Christina Maria to Cardinal Bilio. Place: Rio de Janeiro. Description: Handwritten letter from the empress of Brazil to the cardinal, thanking him for his Christmas greetings, with typescript English summary., 1880 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
    - Author: Long, Thomas J. Title: Notes and Reading Lists on Brazil. Description: Handwritten bound volume of miscellaneous writings, copied from other sources, concerning the Amazon River. Included are typescript letters, charts, biographies of early missionaries, reports about the source of the Amazon, and information on the Plate, Orinoco and Beni Rivers. In English with some Spanish passages. A five page reading list is found at the end of the volume., Circa 1896-1907 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - Portugal
    - Title: Letter by Manoel Godinho Heredia. Place: Lisbon?. Description: Copy of a letter of condolence written by a Portuguese cosmographer to [Francisco de Gama?] between 1597 and 1600 concerning the death of a descendant of Vasco de Gama., 1875 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Lembranza de Baltezar Fr. Gomez." Description: [Seventeenth century?] laudatory letter to (Antonio de Roche?) from Batlezar Gomez. The letter may actually be an order of payment from Gomez's brother Alfonso. The text mentions the Spanish cities of Seville and Cadiz, and Ilha Terceira in the Azores., undated (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
- Additional material, 1856-1895; Accession 2013-M-024
  This accession consists of published illustrated materials related to Brazil, including scenes of the cities of Rio de Janeiro, Sao Paulo, and Bahia.
  - Title: "Nel Brasile--Veduta Di Rio Janeiro Dalla Rada. Photographer: M. Ferrez. Publication: L'Illustrazione Italiana, page 268., Circa 1856-1895 (Box 1)
  - Title: "The Revolution in Brazil--View of San Christovão Where the Winter Residence of the Ex-Empress is Situated." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: The Graphic., Circa 1856-1895 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Sao Paolo Nel Brasile." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: L'Illustrazione Italiana, page 265., Circa 1856-1895 (Box 1)
  - Description: Seven illustrations of buildings, landscapes and street scenes in Brazil. Illustrators: Unknown. Publication: L'Illustrazione Universale, pages 812-813, Circa 1856-1895 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Commencement of the Bahia Railway." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: The Illustrated London News, page 58., 1856 July 19 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Site of the Station at Bahia--From a Photograph by B. Mulock," "Paripe Valley--From a Photograph by B. Mulock." Illustrator: R.P Leitch. Publication: The Illustrated London News, page 382., 1860 October 20 (Box 1)
  - Title: "View of Bahia from the Public Gardens." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: The Illustrated London News, page 577., 1864 November 19 (Box 1)
  - Title: "H.M.S. Galatea Receiving the Emperor of Brazil on His Visit to the H.R.H. the Duke of Edinburgh at Rio De Janeiro." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: The Illustrated London News, page 284., 1867 September 14 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Rio Grande Do Sul, Brazil." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: The Illustrated London News, page 601., 1867 November 30 (Box 1)
  - Title: "The Town of Cameta, in Para, South America." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: The Illustrated London News, page 368., 1868 April 18 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Su e giù Rio Janeiro--Piazza Della Costituzione." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: L'Illustrazione Italiana, page 348., 1879 (Box 1)
  - Title: "The Principe do Gram Para Railway, Brazil." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: The Graphic, page 329., 1883 September 29 (Box 1)
  - Description: Three illustrations depicting the Amazon River. Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: Leisure Hour, pages 759-763., 1888 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Scene in the Rua Primiero Do Marzo, Rio De Janeiro, Brazil." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: Unknown., 1892 (Box 1)
  - Title: "The Revolt in Brazil--Desterro, Santa Catharina, The Headquarters of the Provisional Government." Illustrator: Unknown. Publication: Black and White, page 618., 1893 November 11 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Plan de Rio-De-Janeiro (Brésil)." Illustrator: Unknown. Publisher: Unknown. Atlas Universel., 1895 (Box 1)